Guide to the Department of Biology, Yale University, Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Department of Biology, Yale University, records
1906-1985
RU 418
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
9.25
(16 boxes)
The records consist of correspondence, reports, subject files, and memoranda documenting curriculum, faculty appointments, finance, research, buildings, and students of the Yale Department of Biology. Records concerning the International Society for Cell Biology are also included.
Yale University. Biology Department
General note
Forms part of Yale Record Group 14-B (YRG 14-B), Records of academic departments and programs of the Yale Faculty of Arts and Sciences.
Conditions Governing Access
While this collection as a whole is available for research, parts of it may be restricted due to law, university policy or fragility. Any restricted material will be noted as such.
Arrangement
The records are arranged by accession.
Scope and Contents
The records consist of correspondence, reports, subject files, and memoranda documenting curriculum, faculty appointments, finance, research, buildings, and students of the Yale Department of Biology. Records concerning the International Society for Cell Biology are also included.
Biology -- Research; Biology -- Study and teaching; Universities and colleges -- Administration; Universities and colleges -- Departments; International Society for Cell Biology; Yale University -- Administration; Yale University -- Buildings; Yale University -- Curricula; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University -- Students; Yale University. Biology Department
- Records, 1906-1975; Accession 1975-A-004
  Conditions Governing Access
  Materials in boxes 7-9 are restricted until Jan 1, 2041 as established by Yale Corporation regulations.
  - Department minutes, reports, proposals
    - 1913-1938 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1919-1942 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1920-1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1924-1949 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1926-1928 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1927 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1928 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - 1928-1965 (Box 2, Folder 8 - 9)
    - 1932-1934 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - 1942-1947 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - 1947-1953 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - 1948-1953 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - 1953-1954 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - 1956 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - 1957-1960 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - 1962-1964 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - International Society for Cell Biology
    - Bank statements, 1956-1958 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Bills, 1956-1959 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Constitutions, 1956-1960 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Dues Lists, 1956-1961 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Financial reports and statements, 1956-1962 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Journal, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Membership and candidates lists, 1949-1950 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Minutes, 1949-1950 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - News clippings and releases, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Programs and invitations, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Reports, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Research papers, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 29 - 30)
    - Rules and reports, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Speech by E.W. Sinnott, undated (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - "Suggestions for Preparation of Application for Grant for Research Project", 1948 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Tissue Culture Association, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Correspondence
      - 1947 Apr - 1949 Apr (Box 4, Folder 35)
      - 1949 May - Oct (Box 4, Folder 36)
      - 1949 Nov - 1950 Feb (Box 4, Folder 37)
      - 1950 Mar - Jul (Box 4, Folder 38)
      - 1950 Aug - 1958 Nov (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Kline Biology Tower Construction
    - Proposal, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Application, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - Planning, 1960-1964 (Box 4, Folder 42 - 45)
  - Inventories and Stockroom Reports
    - Narcotics: inventories and laboratory use, 1927-1947 (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - Inventories and stockroom reports, 1929-1949 (Box 5, Folder 47)
    - Alcohol report, 1942-1954 (Box 5, Folder 48)
    - Inventories and stockroom reports, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 49)
    - Inventories and stockroom reports, 1951-1952 (Box 5, Folder 50)
    - Inventories and stockroom reports, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 51)
    - Inventories and stockroom reports, 1952-1954 (Box 5, Folder 52)
    - Inventory: all buildings, 1952-1956 (Box 5, Folder 53)
    - Inventory: JWG, OBL, Marsh, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Biology Department course syllabus and room assignments, 1974-1975 (Box 5, Folder 55)
    - Budget, 1913-1951 (Box 5, Folder 56)
    - Hall correspondence, 1947 (Box 6, Folder 57)
    - Memorabilia, 1924-1957 (Box 6, Folder 58)
    - New York Botanical Garden Correspondence, 1906-1928 (Box 6, Folder 59)
    - Oastler Bequest Committee, 1962-1965 (Box 6, Folder 60)
    - Osborn Zoological Laboratory floor plans, 1913-1940 (Box 6, Folder 61)
    - Physical Facilities Committee, 1962-1965 (Box 6, Folder 62)
    - Prospect Hill School, 1942-1966 (Box 6, Folder 63)
    - Provost's leter, 1961 July 10 (Box 6, Folder 64)
    - Travel requests, 1962-1965 (Box 6, Folder 66)
    - Tri-Institutional Committee (formerly Yale-Bishop Museum Committee), 1962 (Box 6, Folder 67)
  - Appointments and Financial Papers [restricted until Jan 1, 2041]
    - A, 1922-1953 (Box 7, Folder 68)
    - B, 1922-1953 (Box 7, Folder 69)
    - C-L, 1922-1953 (Box 7, Folder 70)
    - M-R, 1922-1953 (Box 7, Folder 71)
    - S, 1922-1953 (Box 7, Folder 72)
    - T-Z, 1922-1953 (Box 7, Folder 73)
    - A-C, 1915-1951 (Box 7, Folder 74)
    - D, 1929-1952 (Box 7, Folder 75)
    - E-F, 1928-1938 (Box 7, Folder 76)
    - G-J, 1925-1952 (Box 7, Folder 77)
    - K-L, 1947-1951 (Box 8, Folder 78)
    - M-N, 1927-1952 (Box 8, Folder 79)
    - P-Z, 1929-1952 (Box 8, Folder 80)
    - A-F, 1925-1928 (Box 8, Folder 81)
    - H-Z, 1925-1928 (Box 8, Folder 82)
    - B, 1940-1953 (Box 8, Folder 83)
    - C-D, 1947-1953 (Box 8, Folder 84)
    - F-G, 1948-1953 (Box 8, Folder 85)
    - H-N, 1940-1953 (Box 8, Folder 86)
    - O-P, 1943-1954 (Box 8, Folder 87)
    - R, 1948-1954 (Box 8, Folder 88)
    - S-Z, 1947-1953 (Box 8, Folder 89)
    - Account with American Cancer Society, 1950-1952 (Box 8, Folder 90)
  - Miscellaneous, 1927-1928 (Box 8, Folder 91)
  - Miscellaneous, 1941-1952 (Box 8, Folder 92)
  - Miscellaneous, 1942-1966 (Box 8, Folder 93)
  - Graduate Students, undated (Box 9, Folder 94)
  - Graduate students' records, grants, certification, correspondence
    - A-C, 1946-1952 (Box 9, Folder 95)
    - D-E, 1941-1952 (Box 9, Folder 96)
    - G-L, 1946-1953 (Box 9, Folder 97)
    - M-Z, 1948-1954 (Box 9, Folder 98)
  - Graduate school, 1962-1964 (Box 9, Folder 99)
  - Letters of recommendation and Faculty resumes, 1938-1964 (Box 9, Folder 100)
  - Provost, 1962-1965 (Box 9, Folder 101)
  - Dean William C. DeVane, 1945-1955 (Box 9, Folder 102)
- Records of Bruce Stowe as chairman of the Dept. of Biology, 1958-1985; Accession 2002-A-094
  Restricted until Jan 1, 2021
  - BPO, 1976-1981 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Faculty Meetings, 1971-1985 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - YCMYØ3, 1983 May (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - YCMY25, 1984 May (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - YCOCØ6, 1983 October (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - YCNOØ3, 1983 November (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - YCDEØ1, 1983 December (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - YCFEØ2, 1984 January (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - YCMRØ1, 1984 March (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - YCOCØ4, 1984 October (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - YCNOØ1, 1984 November (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - YCDEØ6, 1984 December (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - YCFEØ7, 1985 February (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - YCMRØ7, 1985 March (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - US Ph US Grant Apps. and Reports, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - RG6921 02 USPHS, 92-31-42-0402 (STOWE) (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - USPHS GRANT, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - USPHS GRANT, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Roses Transcript, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Roses Literature, 1958-1961 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Roses Financial (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Roses Data and Manuscript (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Roses Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Property Maintenance Budget (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Nat. Sci. Found. Undergraduate Res. Payroll and Treasurer, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Library Periodicals, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - U.S. Public Health Serv. Grant Applications and Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - USPHS GM-06921-10 to -12 Indole Metabolism (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Old Kline Library Comm (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Old Saybrook Files (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - YCAPØ5, 1984 April (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Various loose papers (Box 2, Folder 32 - 35)
  - FAS Restructure (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - DEPT. MEETINGS - Dean Yale College, Chairman Biology, FAS Arts Sci. Yale College, 1978-80 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - LIBRARY - Biology Dept. Library, Kline Library Questionnaire, Kline Library Committee, Library Selection Committee, Various Library Papers-loose-I, Various Library Papers-loose-II (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Library Research and Development Committee (Box 2, Folder 39 - 41)
  - Kline Building Plans (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Grad Students (who never matriculated) (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Board of Permanent Officers (Box 2, Folder 44 - 47)
  - Biochemistry Lab and Appointment Plans, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Various loose papers (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Chairman
    - O. Tippo, Botany Dept, 1958-1960 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - N.H. Giles, Botany Dept., 1960-1961 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - A.W. Galston, Botany Dept., 1961-1962 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - D.F, Poulson, Biology Dept., 1962 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - C.L. Markert, Dept. of Biology (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Dept. Meetings
    - Botany
      - 1959-1960 (Box 3, Folder 55)
      - 1961-1962 (Box 3, Folder 56)
      - 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - Biology
      - 1963-1964 (Box 3, Folder 58)
      - 1964-1965 (Box 3, Folder 59)
      - 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 60)
      - 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 61)
      - 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - Director of Undergraduate Studies, 1971- (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Executive Committee, Biology Dept., 1968-1970 (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - Faculty of Arts and Sciences meetings- more than two years old (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - Field Trip Yale-Harvard-Brown (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Gordon Research Conferences (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - Prophet Center (Box 3, Folder 69 - 71)
  - DGS-Biology, 1966-1975 (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - Business Office, 1972-1976 (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - Forestry and ES School, 1977-1982 (Box 3, Folder 74)
- Osborn Memorial Labs renovation proposal, 1983; Accession 2009-A-039
  - Osborn Memorial Labs renovation proposal, 1983 (Box 1)
- Frank Ruddle, Professor Emeritus, records, Circa 1976-2005; Accession 2010-A-066; 1.5 linear feet (3 boxes)
  Materials contained in boxes 1 and 2 are restricted until January 1, 2041 due to University policy. Materials in box 3 are open for research.
  - Biology Department, 1987-1998 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    Material is closed until January 1, 2041 due to University policy.
  - Biological Sciences Advisory Committee, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Biospheric Institute Committee, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Committee on Division V and report of the visiting committee, Circa 1988 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Committee to Review Program in Ecology and Evolution, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Comprehensive Cancer Center, 1988-1996 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Search Committee, Developmental Vertebrate Biology, 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Faculty Club Committee, 1976-1988 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Giamatti, A. Bartlett, 1983, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Genetics Search Committee, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Graduate School, 1997-1999
    - Dean Search Committee, 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Executive Committee, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 14-15)
    - Graduate School Assembly, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Immunology Search Committee, 1986-1990 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Obstetrics/Gynecology Search Committee, 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Organismal Biology Search Committee, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Peabody Museum Search Committee, 1987-1994 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Physiology Search Committee, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - President's Report, 1989-1997 (Box 1, Folder 22-29)
  - Report of Committee on Yale School of Nursing, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Route 34 Biomedical Park Board, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Science Park, 1992-2004
    - Audit Committee, 1994-2001 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Board of Directors, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 36, Box 1, Folder 35)
    - President Search Committee, 2001-2004 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Senior Appointments Committee, 1987-2001 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Sponsored Research Committee, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Staff, 1977-1994 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Tenure Appointments in Biological Sciences, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Terry Lecture Committee, 1991-1992 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Yale College Deanship Search Committee, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Yale Science and Engineering Association, 1985-1992 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Yale, 1997-2005 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Curriculum vita and biography, 1995-2004 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Photographs, Circa 2000 (Box 3, Folder 48)